Mathew Wheatley

mathew.p.wheatley@gmail.com
www.github.com/mathewpwheatley

Los Angeles, CA (301) 481-6219

in www.linkedin.com/in/mathewpwheatley

www.mathewpwheatley.medium.com

Professional Summary

I am a results-oriented engineer with 10 years of experience and a proven history of problem solving in challenging fields ranging from aircraft and rocket engine design to e-commerce. My experience gives me an understanding of the importance of each aspect of engineering from requirements definition, research, design, analysis, integration, teamwork, testing, and maintenance. I am excited to tackle new problems that will make this world a better place.

Professional Experience

Back-end Software Developer Intern - Commerce Intelligence

Shopify

Seattle, WA (Remote)

🗰 January 2021 - Present

- ▶ Closely collaborated with interfacing teams via frequent paired programming as well as code reviews in a continuous integration environment.
- Implemented type checking via Sorbet on numerous modules to ensure data is properly structured and the code is semantically explicit.
- Successful execution of cursor based GraphQL pagination on a Ruby on Rails back-end service to serve customer facing activity log.
- ▶ Wrote and maintained well-tested code on Ruby on Rails back-end which served data for merchant insights.
- Actively sought out growth opportunities to expand my skill set while balancing all deliverables.

Propulsion Engineer III - BE-3 & BE-3U Rocket Engine Turbopumps

Blue Origin

Seattle, WA

December 2015 - September 2019

- Critical and timely redesign in response to life shortfall due to vibrational issues on the BE-3 liquid hydrogen turbopump turbine rotor.
- ▶ Test data trending against design analysis predictions to verify performance and integrity as well as gain insight into any shortfalls or unforeseen issues.
- Created critical assembly stack verification via drop measurements, torque tests, and helium leak tests.
- Oversaw of design, analysts, manufacturing, integration, and test engineers with a average team size of five.
- Development of wiki to act as the single source of truth for design, block updates, procurement, schedule, and testing for the BE-3 turbopumps.
- Schedule along with resource planning of design, procurement, inspection, assembly, and integration dates for BE-3 turbopump development as well as production.
- Authoring of two executive level memorandums describing technical issues and recommended path forward.

Design Engineer - AETD Aircraft Engine High Pressure Turbine & Compressor Rotor

Cincinnati, OH

iii June 2012 - November 2015

- Design of eight critical rotating parts in the compressor of the AETD jet engine.
- Preparation as well as presentation of numerous design reviews at various stages of design to chief engineers, management, and other top level stakeholders such as the Air Force.
- Structural, thermal, and vibrational analysis of critical static as well as rotating hardware using the appropriate tools ranging from hand calculations, home grown code, and finite element analysis.

Control Systems Engineer - GEnx-1B Aircraft Engine FADEC

Cincinnati, OH

📅 October 2010 - June 2012

- ▶ Logic design and implementation of various valves on the GEnx-1B aircraft engine.
- ▶ GEnx-1B squawk lead responsible for delegating, management, and resolution of flight test issues.
- Logic verification on HIL, engine test, and flight test.

Education History

- **Software Engineering**
- Flatiron School

- Seattle, WA
- iii March 2020 July 2020

- Masters of Science in Mechanical Engineering
- The Ohio State University

- Columbus, OH
- Bachelors of Science in Mechanical Engineering
- university of Maryland, Baltimore County
- Paltimore, MD
- 3.46 GPA
- 🛗 September 2012 May 2014
- September 2006 August 2010

Toolbox Summary

Languages

- Ruby
- Javascript
- Typescript
- Python
- ▶ HTML
- CSS
- Markdown
- YAML
- SOL

Notable Libraries

- Minitest
- Sorbet
- Redux
- Thunk
- GraphQL-Ruby

Frameworks & SDK

Ruby on Rails

Apollo

React

Flutter

Postgres Sequel Pro

Database

- Collaboration Miro
 - Zenhub
 - Git & Github
 - Tuple
 - Slack

Design

- Photoshop
- Lightroom
- Illustrator
- Premier Pro
- Inkscape
- Figma

IDE

- ▶ iTerm
- VS Code

CAD

- PTC Creo
- NX Unigraphics
- Fusion 360

Other

- Matlab
- Ansys Workbench/ADPL

Personal Projects

Brewery Run

■ Demo □ Hosted ☐ Front-end ☐ Back-end

A web-app enabling users to create, share, and discover running routes between local breweries.

- Implemented secure login to Rails API back-end via JWT tokens stored in secure http only cookies
- ▶ Built React based app which utilizes Redux store with asynchronous fetches to back-end via middle-ware Thunk.
- Interfaced with several APIs including Google Maps and Open Brewery DB.
- Safeguarded user data by conditionally provided data based on user and rendering requirements.

Technical & Leadership Credentials

Professional

- Edison Engineering Program at GE
- Advanced Course in Engineering at GE
- Geometric Dimensioning & Tolerance
- Foundations of Leadership at GE
- Mechanical Design Fundamentals at GE
- Engineer in Training (EIT) Certification
- **==** 2011 - 2013

- 2011
- 2010

== 2019

2015

2015

== 2014 - 2015

2013 - 2015

iii 2012 - 2015

<u>===</u> 2010 - 2015

Volunteerism

- Teaching & Construction Abroad
- The World Is Fun Event Lead
- ▶ FIRST Robotics Robot Inspector
- GBB Lead Coordinator
- Paint The Town Committee
- GBC Hands-On Committee
- Give Back Beyond (GBBC) Volunteer
- Give Back Cincinnati (GBC) Volunteer

- 2012

Extracurricular Pursuits

- Laser Cutting
- Wood working
- Leather working
- 3D Printing
- Photography
- Running Climbing
- Skiing
- Hiking
- Drones





